In days lecture we will understand Docker volumes and how to use them in Dockerize.net apps.
Volumes are persistent data stores for containers.
Here you can keep your data so that it remains safe even if the container crashes.
Volumes are stored within the directory of the Docker host which is our PC
and so when we mount a volume into a container this directory is what's mounted into the container.
The picture explains Docker volumes. Here is the container which is referencing a Docker volume.
This volume contains important files for the apps and is stored outside the container on the
local PC where Docker desktop is installed. So this means the app files are safe even if the container
crashes. Let us understand the concept of Docker volume but the help of an ASP.net core website.
This is my website and let me run it.
The purpose of this website is to collect people's name and email addresses who visits this website.
People are shown a very attractive message saying you are the lucky chosen one for an iPhone
gift. Submit your name and email to get iPhone delivered to you. Think about you visit this website
and submit your details then your details are safe on the website. The safe details are seen
at the user page. Let me submit a couple more entries on this website.
You can see every details are safe.
[no audio]
Let us understand a little bit about the coding part. The index action inside the home
controller saves the user details in a text file. Here directly called emails is created
then a text file called user data.txt is created inside the emails folder and we save the username
and emails of the persons per line in comma separated manner. These details of users are saved
in a text file inside emails folder. The file name is userdata.txt. You can see the text file
saved data here. Each user data is saved per line in comma separated manner. The index view file
contains the form where user can submit his or her details. You can see the code here.
[no audio]
Moving to the user action method in the home controller which reads the user data from
the text file and shows them in HTML table format. This is the code doing this task. The user view
code contains an HTML form where we show all the submitted data of the users. Now we will
dockerize this ASP.NET Core website. First we delete the emails folder since all user entries
will be created again. Next we add Docker support to this website by right-clicking the project
name and selecting add, then select Docker support option. In the container scaffolding window,
keep all the default details and click the OK button. Now open websites folder in file explorer.
We can now close Visual Studio and then open docker desktop where you can see Visual Studio has
created the websites image by the name of lucky winner. Delete this image since we will build a
new image through docker commands. So this is the websites folder and here is the docker file.
Now we open the PowerShell on this location. We now run docker build command type docker space build
space -t then specify the name of the image which can be anything of your choice. I am naming
it lucky winner colon v1 then space -f space docker file space dot.
This is the whole command. Then press enter you can see image is building and let's wait for a few
seconds to complete.
OK it's now build successfully. On docker desktop you can see this image.
We now run a container for this image. The command is docker run. So type docker space run space -name
space specify the name of the container. I am naming it lucky winner then type -p flag and give the
port mappings 5,000 to for host port and 8080 for the container port.
Then specify the image name which is lucky winner colon v1.
See this is the whole command. Now press enter. Okay the container is created now and we can see
the message listening on local host colon 8080. We can now open the website on the Chrome browser.
So type local host colon 5,002 which is the host port then press enter. See here is the website
opening and this time the website is opening from the docker container. We can now add some people
details to this website like before. You can see they are saving correctly on the website.
No bad this time they are saving on the container.
Open docker desktop you can see the image and the container of the website. Let us analyze the
data of the users that is saved in the container. Open a new PowerShell tab. Here type docker
ps command and this will show the containers running the website. This is the container ID. Now type
docker exec dash it dash u root then container id then dash and then press enter. This is the
bass session inside the Linux container. Here type ls command to see all the directories and files.
This is the emails directory which is storing the user details. Let us enter inside this directory with
cd emails command then type ls command to see all the files inside this directory. Here is the user
data dot txt file. We can open this file with the cat command of Linux. Type cat user data dot txt
and here you can see the user details. These are the same which the website is showing.
Everything is working properly but problems can come any time. Suppose due to an outrage this
container crashes then we have to spin a new container for our dotnet apps image. Let's create this scenario.
We first stop the container by docker stop lucky winner command.
Then remove this container by docker rm lucky winner command.
After this we spin a new container by the same docker run command which we ran earlier.
Now on the website refresh it you can see there is no data because the data is lost.
Probably the emails folder containing them is also lost. We can check this by running
the best session as we did earlier.
We are now inside the container and we run ls command shows there is no emails folder.
So this confirms that we have lost our data. Therefore remember whenever container crashes
the data is also lost. Now we will understand how to prevent this data loss when the container
is crashed. The solution is obviously docker volumes. We will use docker volumes to create
a persistent data stored. We will create a directory on our local pc on drive d and this will serve
as a volume. The directory is what's mounted on the container. Now we will stop and remove the
running container and will recreate this container. So first run docker ps command to get the container
id then stop the container using docker stop then container id and finally remove this container
from the docker desktop by docker rm container id command. Let's create a new container with volumes
mounted to it. The command is docker run -p to give the port mappings here type 5000 to colon 8080
then type -v flag which stands for volumes. Here we first give the absolute part of the directory
on the local machine that will serve as the volumes. This part is d colon / emails. You can choose
any part of your choice. After that type colon and here we have to give the part on the container
where this directory will be mounted. This part is / apps / emails folder. Recall the website
was saving the user's data inside the emails folder. Right then type the image name which is
lucky winner colon b1. I would also like you to show my pc's d drive. Here you can see there is no
emails folder right now. When I press enter you can see the emails folder is created on the d drive.
Now the container is running with volumes mounted on it. Let's create some user increase
and test the persistence of the data.
You can see all data is saved.
We again do the same thing. Stop the container then remove it.
You can think about this that the container is crashed. Now we have to spin a new container for
our website's image. Again we run the same command, docker, run, -p,
-5,02 colon 8080 -v,d colon / emails colon / apps / emails lucky winner colon v1.
Before I press enter I want to show that the emails folder on the d drive contains the user
data.txt file which is saving the user details. Okay and let's press enter to run the command.
See fresh d browser and you can see the data has persisted. Congratulations we have implemented
docker volumes in our esp.net code website. We now go inside the container. So in docker desktop click
the container's name then on exe tab run ls command then go inside the emails directory with cd emails
command and then with ls command again to cd user data.txt file. Let's make a directory xyz with
mkdir xyz command. Look the directory is created. If we check the emails folder on d drive you
can see the xyz directory is created. Now let's make a new text file and name it abc
here we see a text cats are good friends of man
We now check this file inside the container type ls and here you can see abc.txt file
To open this file we use the cat command of line x type cat abc.txt
So here you see the same text cats are good friends of man. I hope with this you are able to
understand how docker volumes work. Before we end this lecture let's discuss primary uses of docker
volumes. First is the data persistence of files that contain some important data. Second is database
management. We can store database files so they will be saved outside the container and this way
database data is saved in case of container crashes. Third is data sharing between multiple
containers. This is helpful in microservices architecture. You can now download the source code
of dsp.net.co website and run all these steps I've done in this lecture.